Brazil Railway Company Records, 1914-1920: A Finding Aid
Brazil Railway Company records, 1914-1920
Baker Library, Harvard Business School
Mss:724 1914-1920 B827
Brazil Railway Company
9 linear ft. (19 vols. and 8 boxes)
The Brazil Railway Company records include administrative material, financial records, and letters and papers pertaining to the reorganization of the company spearheaded by W. Cameron Forbes, 1914-1920.
Provenance:
Gift of W.Cameron Forbes through Harvard College Library, 1951.
Appointment necessary to consult collection.
Historical Note:
The Brazil Railway Company was founded in 1906 by New York businessman and Latin American industrialist Percival Farquhar. He had a dream of industrializing the Southern Amazon region by building railways to carry and distribute goods and materials. In 1913, the Brazil Railway Company filed for bankruptcy due to the Balkan Wars and a freeze in credit. A court in Maine appointed W. Cameron Forbes as receiver of the company and he created a reorganization and credit pay back plan for the company. The Brazil Railway continued to operate until roughly 1940.
Scope and Content Note:
The records of the Brazil Railway Company include receivership journals, administrative records, financial material, reports, and letters. The material documents the reorganization of the company after it filed for bankruptcy in 1913 and W. Cameron Forbes' attempt to repay debts and restore the company to a profit making enterprise. Also included is correspondence of co-receiver Charles E. Perkins and records relating to the Brazil Land, Cattle, and Packing Co., the Madeira-Mamoré Railway, and the Uruguay Railway Company.
Additional material concerning W. Cameron Forbes can be found in the Forbes family business records, which are also held at Baker Library. Mss:766 1803-1942 F693
Container List
- Brazil Railway receivership journal, October 13, 1914-June 7, 1915 (v. NB-1)
- Brazil Railway receivership journal, June 2-September 30, 1915 (v. NB-2)
- Brazil Railway receivership journal, October 1-December 31, 1915 (v. NB-3)
- Brazil Railway receivership journal, January 1-March 31, 1916 (v. NB-4)
- Brazil Railway receivership journal, April 1-July 31, 1916 (v. NB-5)
- Brazil Railway receivership journal, August 1-December 31, 1916 (v. NB-6)
- Brazil Railway receivership journal, January 2-March 31, 1917 (v. NB-7)
- Madeira-Mamoré Railway receivership journal, April 1-December 31, 1917 (v. NB-8)
  Includes X index.
- Madeira-Mamoré Railway receivership journal, August 1-December 31, 1917 (v. NB-9)
  Includes XI index.
- Madeira-Mamoré Railway receivership journal, January 1-June 30, 1918 (v. NB-10)
  Includes XII index.
- Madeira-Mamoré Railway receivership journal, July 1-December 31, 1918 (v. NB-11)
  Includes XIII index.
- Madeira-Mamoré Railway receivership journal, January 1-December 31, 1919 (v. NB-12)
  Includes XIV index.
- Brail Railway receivership journals index (v. NB-13)
- Report on railway properties in Southern Brazil, September 15, 1916 (v. NB-14)
  Report on the railway properties in southern Brazil, leased, owned, or controlled by the Brazil Railway Company, by F.A. Moliter, September 15, 1916.
- Reports, 1916 (v. NB-15)
  Reports generated on May 1, 1916 by Charles E. Perkins on the Brazil Land, Cattle, Packing Company and the Uruguay Railway Co.
- Exhibits to the report of receiver W. Cameron Forbes (v. NB-16)
- Memoirs (v. NB-17)
  Memoirs probably kept for a report.
- Form records of component railways (v. NB-18)
- New York Trust Co. checks (v. NB-19)
- Letters and papers, 1914-1918 (Box NB-20)
  Letters and papers kept from October 1914-September 1915, largely organized alphabetically. H.S. Gordon file kept, 1916-1917 and material related to co-receiver Charles E. Perkins, December 1917-September 1918.
- Letters and papers, 1917-1920 (Box NB-21)
  Letters and papers largely kept by Charles E. Perkins from1917-1920. Also includes papers and accounts of the Brazil Land, Cattle, and Packing Co., 1915-1918.
- Farquhar files (Box NB-22)
  This box contains material of the Farquhar file including a Charles A. Gauld's partial manuscript on Percival Farquhar (gift of Gauld) and papers relating to W. Cameron Forbes and his role as receiver of the Brazil Railway Company.
- Reorganization dossier, #1-4 (Box NB-23)
- Reorganization dossier, #5-6 (Box NB-24)
- Confidential letters, nos. 1-107 (Box NB-25)
- Confidential letters and reorganization papers, 1917-1919 (Box NB-26)
- Photographs (Box NB-27)
Additional catalog entries
The following catalog entries represent persons, organizations, and topics documented in this collection. An entry for each appears in the Harvard On Line Library Information System (HOLLIS) and other automated bibliographic databases. THIS IS NOT AN INDEX.
Authors
Farquhar, Percival, 1864-1953.; Forbes, W. Cameron (William Cameron), 1870-1859.; Gauld, Charles Anderson, 1911-; Perkins, Charles E.
Subjects
Railroads--Brazil.; Railroads -- South America.; Transportation.; Photographs; Brazil Land, Cattle, and Packing Company.; Ferrovia Madeira-Mamoré.; Uruguay Railway Company.